This is דף פ' Daf Pei 80,
and we are in the middle of אותו ואת בנו Oto ve-et
Beno and exploring the whole question about fatherhood amongst the mammals and
the humans.
So we pick up actually at the bottom of פ' עמוד ב'
Pei Amud Bet
and we are, let's see where we are,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 lines before the lines
get wide and we'll start from the beginning of the line. רבנן,
Rabbanan, and the rabbis. So the גמרא Gemara here is dealing with
this whole question about this כוי Koy which as we'll see later
in today's דף, daf, there actually was people knew that we were
talking about some weird animal but they apparently was not even clear
where it came from because we've been assuming that it came from
a crossbreed between a goat and a צבי tzvi which sounds like
it means which means a deer but could mean other things as
we discussed earlier in חולין, Chullin, but it's hard to imagine how
those crossbreeds, anyway later the גמרא Gemara will say that maybe it's
actually its own breed. So at least here we believe that it's
a crossbreed between a בהמה beheimah and a חיה. chayah. And the
question is, what's its status? So to some degree the question is,
well, who is the mother and do you also factor in the
father? So if the mother is a חיה, chayah, then it's at
least part חיה, chayah, and whether you factor in the father determines
whether it's also part בהמה, beheimah, or vice versa, depending on the
mother who the father is. So far we had that discussion in
אותו ואת בנו. Oto ve-et Beno. We said אותו ואת בנו Oto
ve-et Beno the child doesn't matter, it's the mother that has to
be
a בהמה. beheimah. So if the mother is a כוי, Koy, then
it has to be בהמה. beheimah. Is it enough that it be
part בהמה? beheimah? Does it have to be full בהמה? beheimah? etc.
So we've been assuming it's enough that the mother be part בהמה,
beheimah, that this כוי Koy was born from, the mother was a
צבי. tzvi. So the question is, if you include the father in
this identity, at least it's part בהמה beheimah and it's in אותו
ואת בנו. Oto ve-et Beno. If you don't, then it's not part
בהמה, beheimah, then it's not. Fine. Then we moved on to the
question of the position that there's a ספק safek whether you have
to cover its blood, which also ספק safek of a חיה, chayah,
which also means that you don't know if,
which means that you can't שחט shacht on יום טוב Yom Tov
because you don't want to be in a position where you have
to cover its blood but aren't certain and therefore aren't able. So
the question is, what makes it a ספק? safek? How do you
understand how it's a ספק? safek? Until now we've been saying it
all depends on your position about whether you count the father or
not. So it says, well, remember there's a possibility that we have
a ספק safek whether to consider the father. So we will assume
that we're talking about a case where the mother was a בהמה,
beheimah, the father was a חיה, chayah, and it's a ספק safek
whether you consider the father's contribution or not. So this thing is
a ספק safek partial חיה. chayah. And because of that, because of
the father's parentage but the question whether we consider it, that makes
it a ספק חיה safek chayah and a ספק safek whether you
cover the blood. So we're going to pick up from there. Yes.
Is there a ברכה bracha for covering the blood?
Yes, and you don't make it in the case of a ספק.
safek. Okay, so now again, eight lines before the lines get wide:
רבנן ספוקי מספקא להו. Rabbanan sapuki mesapka le-hu. So the rabbis therefore
have a doubt: אי חוששין לזרע האב אי לא חוששין, i choshishin
le-zera ha-av i lo choshishin, if you consider the contribution of the
father or not. And therefore this animal, because the father was a
חיה, chayah, is a ספק safek half חיה chayah and therefore a
ספק safek whether you cover the blood. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ולרבנן מספקא להו? u-le-Rabbanan mesapka le-hu? So now that you're saying that
the rabbis have a doubt, והרבי אליעזר פטרה לה? ve-ha-Rabbi Eliezer patrah
lah? It sounds like according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's certainly
you do not include the parentage of the father, okay? And you
could have inferred that because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is not concerned
for אותו ואת בנו Oto ve-et Beno if the father is a
בהמה. beheimah. So for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you definitely are not
concerned with the contribution of the father. Okay, so now we're going
to, so fine, that all fits with what we've learned so far.
But now we have
a question: והדתניא, ve-ha-detanya, הזרוע לחיים וקיבה ha-zero'a lechayayim ve-keivah נוהגים בכוי
ובכלאים. nohegin be-Koy u-ve-kilayim. הזרוע לחיים וקיבה, Ha-zero'a lechayayim ve-keivah, the gift
you give to the כהן Kohen when you שחט shacht an animal,
do not apply to a חיה. chayah. So here we have a
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that says that it does apply to a
כוי. Koy. So במאי עסקינן? be-mai askinan? Sorry, did I skip a
line?
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כלאים הבא מן העז ומן הרחל
חייב במתנות. kilayim ha-ba min ha-ez u-min ha-rachel chayav be-matanot. I'll grant
you when it's a כלאים kilayim that comes from a sheep and
a goat, therefore it's definitely in the בהמה beheimah world. אבל מן
הכוי פטור מן המתנות, avel min ha-Koy patur min ha-matanot, but not
from the כוי. Koy. Alright, so here again we have this debate
that the rabbis say you do and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
you don't. And it's going to be pretty I think clear how
we're going to explain this. Because remember now we set it up
that the rabbis say we might consider the father's contribution and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says we definitely don't. And we know that מתנות
matanot are only from
בהמה. beheimah. So we're going
to, the case is the mother... The mother is a חיה, chayah,
the father is a בהמה. behemah. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, you definitely don't care about the father, so there's no no
gift, no זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zeroah lechayayim vekeivah. And according to the
and according to the rabbis you might consider the father, so at
least there's at least maybe partial gifts, at least we think. Let's
see let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
It says כיוצא בו אם בא
מן העז ומן הרחל.
keyotzei bo im
ba min ha-ez u-min ha-rachel.
If it's a crossbreed of sheep and goat and it's from the
בהמה behemah world, just those.
Yes, just those. Which usually means no, I mean just those.
Right, exactly. Okay, so now let's see.
So the גמרא Gemara says gifts to the
כהן, kohen, right, from from slaughtering an animal. But it's only from
a חיה, chayah, right, from a from a non-קרבן. korban.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what's the case? אילימא
בתייא שהבא על הצביה, eileima betaya she-ba al ha-tviyah, which is what
we would have assumed, right, you have a תייא taya a goat
that has that mates with a female צבי tzvi deer we'll say
for argument's sake, וילדה ve-yaldah and it had and it had a
child and that's a כוי. koy. So that's what we would have
assumed, that that's an animal that is a questionable half-בהמה. behemah. So
בשלמא לרבי אליעזר, bishlama le-Rabbi Eliezer, I understand רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
דפטר depatur he exempts from the gifts, קסבר שהיה אפילו מקצת לא
אמרינן, kasavar she-haya afilu mikztas lo amrinan, the fact that it might
be that that we don't say it's a partial בהמה behemah that
שהיה אפילו מקצת. she-haya afilu mikztas. Ah, at least it's half a
בהמה, behemah, that's not relevant why? Because he says that we don't
consider the contribution of the father. So it's not it's not a
half-בהמה, behemah, it's a full חיה. chayah. אלא לרבנן, ela le-rabanan, but
for the rabbis, נהי דקסברי שהיה אפילו מקצת, nehi de-kasvari she-haya afilu
mikztas,
we understand that normally they say that if it's part בהמה behemah
it matters, but בשלמא, bishlama, but פלגא לא יהבי, palga lo yahavi,
but let's figure this out. So this animal is definitely part חיה,
chayah, possibly part בהמה. behemah. So the the part of it that
is definitely part חיה, chayah, the fifty percent that is unquestionably part
חיה, chayah, you're not going to give those gifts. Now this is
interesting because as opposed to something like a prohibition of זרוע לחיים
וקיבה zeroah lechayayim vekeivah where you could say, I mean a prohibition
of אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et beno where you could say if
it's part בהמה behemah it's prohibited and therefore you get lashings, we're
not going to say you only get half of the lashings because
it was only half of a בהמה. behemah. We're going to say
if it was a בהמה behemah part בהמה behemah it's prohibited you
get lashings. But for something like a gift to the כהן, kohen,
we're able to translate its sort of its partial identity into a
partial, you know, practical impact, you know, consequence. So therefore if an
animal were let's say definitely half-בהמה half-חיה behemah chayah and the principle
was you only give זרוע לחיים וקיבה zeroah lechayayim vekeivah from a
בהמה, behemah then if you would give half of the gifts to
the כהן, kohen, you know, you'd give half of the זרוע, zeroah,
half of the לחיים. lechayayim. That's the assumption the גמרא Gemara makes.
It didn't have to make that assumption. It could say once it's
in the category, it's in fully, you're not either half of the.
But the גמרא Gemara is assuming you would say that. So it
says if this really were half-בהמה half-חיה, behemah chayah I get I
get it that you would not give half of the gifts from
the חיה chayah part, but you would give half from the בהמה
behemah, part. But this is, we just said the rabbis say that
it's questionable whether you consider the father's contribution. So even on the
half that's a בהמה, behemah it's not certain that you really have
to give anything to the כהן. kohen. The half that's a חיה
chayah, you definitely don't give, the half that's a בהמה behemah is
not certain. So let's take a look. Wait, let's finish what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. Okay, so it says בשלמא פלגא לא יהבי,
bishlama palga lo yahavi, I understand you're not going to give half
of the gifts because it's it's definitely half a חיה. chayah ואידך
פלגא, ve-idach palga, the other half that's possibly half-בהמה, behemah, לימא ליה
לכהן leima leih le-kohen say to the כהן, kohen, אייתי ראיה דחוששין
לזרע האב ושקול. aiti reyah de-chosheshin le-zera ha-av u-shekul.
Look, you go ahead, you prove that it's really a בהמה, behemah
right?
המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה.
hamotzi me-chavero
alav ha-reyah.
Right, exactly. So that's the גמרא's Gemara problem. Why are you giving
any gifts even according to the רבנן? rabanan? The only reason you
would give the gifts is because it's half-בהמה. behemah, But it's questionable
half-בהמה. behemah, It might be full חיה, chayah you might ignore the
father. And therefore, the כהן, kohen, it's a monetary issue, there's a
question whether the כהן kohen deserves these gifts or not. It's pure
דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. So the person who's coming to extract the
money has the burden of proof. So I'll take the position that
a כוי koy is a full חיה, chayah. you go ahead and
prove otherwise. So why how could it be that according to the
rabbis you actually would ever have to give a gift in this
case? So אלא, ela, all right, so let's try to reverse the
case. בצבי הבא על התיישה. bi-tzvi ha-ba al ha-tayasha. So it is
a צבי tzvi a חיה chayah, that mates with a female goat.
So therefore it is definitely at least fifty percent בהמה, behemah. right,
because the mother is the goat. It's at least fifty percent בהמה.
behemah. So now the question is going to be, how would רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say you don't give anything? Since everybody agrees that
it's at least fifty percent בהמה behemah, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would really say it's a hundred percent בהמה behemah. because רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer rejects the father. So let's take a look. בשלמא לרבנן
מאי יהבי, bishlama le-rabanan mai yahavi,
I understand the rabbis what do you give, בחד מתנות, be-chad matanot,
you give half because it's at least fifty percent בהמה. behemah אלא
לרבי אליעזר, ela le-Rabbi Eliezer, but according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
if the mother is a בהמה, behemah לחיב בכולהו מתנות, lechayev be-kulu
matanot,
so you have to give all of them because we he totally
rejects the father's contribution. So this doesn't make any sense, we can't
figure this out once you assume that the rabbis have a ספק
safek about the father's contribution rather than say you definitely include the
father's contribution. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם בצבי הבא על התיישה,
le-olam bi-tzvi ha-ba al ha-tayasha, let's go back to what we were
saying, I mean what we just said, the mother is a... The
mother is a בהמה, behemah. the mother is a goat, and the
father is the חיה, chayah, is the צבי, tzvi, וילדה. ve-yaldah. Okay,
and therefore, so how could רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say no gifts?
It’s 50% בהמה, behemah, actually according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it’s
100% בהמה. behemah, So גמרא Gemara says רבי אליעזר נמי ספקי מספקא
ליה אי חושינן לזרע האב או לא. Rabbi Eliezer nami sukei mesafeka
lei i chosheshinan le-zera ha-av o lo. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer also
thinks that maybe you consider the father’s contribution. So now one minute,
if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer thinks maybe you consider the father’s contribution
and the רבנן Rabbanim think it, what are they debating about? They’re
saying the exact same position. And also why here does רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer say zero and the חכמים Chachamim say you do give
the gift? So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara asks
that, דכיון דרבנן מספקא להו ולרבי אליעזר מספקא להו, de-kivan de-rabbanan mesafeka
lehu u-Rebbi Eliezer mesafeka lehu, במאי פליגי? b’mai palgi? Since the רבנן
Rabbanim don’t know whether you include the father’s contribution and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer doesn’t know, במאי פליגי, b’mai palgi, what are they debating
about? They’re both having the same position. So the גמרא Gemara says
ah no, they debate about whether when something has a half-heritage whether
it matters. שה אפילו מקצת שה. seh afilu miktzas seh. Remember we
have been assuming until now if something is like a half בהמה
behemah, you get לא תשחט אותו ואת בנו. lo sishchos oso ve-es
beno. If it’s a half בהמה behemah. you would give at least
some of the מתנות. matanos. But maybe not. Maybe I could take
a position that even if you know even if something is a
half בהמה behemah it doesn’t count. Half isn’t enough, you need to
be a full בהמה behemah to be into the category. So both
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן Rabbanim agree that in terms
of the question of does the father’s contribution matter, they both agree
that they don’t know. Okay,
the question is then also what criteria do you have in all
these various areas about whether you need full you know full identity
of a בהמה behemah or whether partial identity is enough. And now
we’re going to work it through all the things we’ve discussed. אותו
ואת בנו oso ve-es beno we know is debated רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the רבנן, Rabbanim, the gift the מתנות matanos of the
כהונה kehunah are debated, and the idea that covering the blood is
a ספק. safek. And we’re going to see how we can figure
out all these permutations. And we’re going to work through this right
now.
Does this mean that it’s accepted as an animal or whether however
it is commonly accepted that this is considered what, a כוי koi
or an I mean...
No,
it has nothing to do with what people consider. It has to
do with whether it's who its father, who its mother is and
whether הלכה halachah gives recognition to that.
Talk about בהמה חיה behemah chayah but wouldn’t be considered טריפה treif
in other words?
Oh yeah, בהמה behemah חיה chayah is not a טריפה treif question.
בהמה behemah חיה chayah, is a question about אותו ואת בנו, oso
ve-es beno, gifts to the כהן, kohen, blood, חלב, cheilev, all of
those. All right. Yeah, it’s definitely kosher, right. Okay,
yeah, yeah.
And we had a specific לימוד limud before like limiting these things
from קרבנות, korbanot, right? Yeah, because otherwise then they could have debated
whether even bring it as a קרבן. korban.
Yeah, but no, yeah, certainly yeah, it’s not the idea.
כלאים kilayim is even כלאים kilayim of two בהמות behemos is not
a קרבן, korban, correct. Okay, so let’s continue יום טוב, Yom Tov,
I’m just trying to tweak this. Okay, that should be... Fine. So
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Yeah. What’s... What? Yeah, one of his two mating of two goat
species. What? Both either of which both the father...
what would that be in terms of קרבנות korbanos for example? That
should be fine because I don’t think הלכה halachah distinguishes between goat
species even if you do in science. Okay. So גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now we’re going to figure now we’re going to say
how it all plays out. רבנן סברי שה אפילו מקצת שה, Rabbanan
savrei seh afilu miktzas seh, the רבנן Rabbanim normally are willing to
consider something that even partial בהמה behemah as having fitting into a
בהמה behemah category.
רבי אליעזר סברי שה ולא מקצת שה. Rabbi Eliezer savrei seh ve-lo
miktzas seh. No, if something is only a partial בהמה behemah it
doesn’t count. If something wants to if there’s a requirement for a
בהמה, behemah, it has to be a full בהמה. behemah. And now
how does that work out in all these cases? רב פפא Rav
Pappa is going to spell it out for us. So אמר רב
פפא, amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הילכך, hilkach, therefore,
let me tell you how it works. לעניין כיסוי הדם ומתנות, le-inyan
kisuy ha-dam u-matanos, when it comes to covering the blood and the
gifts to the כהן, kohen, לא משכחת אלא בצבי הבא על התיישה.
lo mashkachas ela be-tzvi ha-ba al ha-teishah.
So here’s the case. The case is that a if the צבי,
tzvi, the חיה, chayah, male חיה chayah mated with the female בהמה,
behemah, the תיישה, teishah, the goat. So again so what’s that case?
It’s definitely half בהמה behemah and part possibly half חיה. chayah. Okay?
דבין לרבנן ובין לרבי אליעזר מספקא להו אי חושינן לזרע האב או
לא. de-vein le-rabbanan u-vein le-Rabbi Eliezer mesafeka lehu i chosheshinan le-zera ha-av
o lo.
Rabbis and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer don’t know if you consider the
father’s contribution, whether you consider this to also be a partial חיה,
chayah, but it is at least as a half בהמה. behemah. וקמיפלגי
בשה אפילו מקצת שה. ve-ka miflegi b’seh afilu miktzas seh.
And they debate the עניין inyan of שה אפילו מקצת שה. seh
afilu miktzas seh. What does that mean? So it means like this.
It’s definitely partial בהמה, behemah, you don’t know if it is full
בהמה. behemah. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says partial בהמה behemah isn’t
enough. I don’t know if you’re חייב chayav in זרוע לחיים וקיבה
zero'a lechayayim ve-kiva to the כהן kohen because maybe it’s only a
half בהמה behemah and if it was only a half you wouldn't
have to. If you’re not all, you’re nothing. So therefore what I
say to the כהן kohen is this animal might only be a
half בהמה behemah and therefore you don’t get anything and you can’t
prove that it’s a full בהמה, behemah, goodbye. That’s what I say
if I’m רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. If I’m the רבנן Rabbanim though
what do I say? I say I have to concede the half
בהמה. behemah. Half בהמה behemah is enough to give you half of
the מתנות. matanot. I don’t give you the... The other half, that's
debatable, but at least I have to give you a half. So
that's why they debate the מתנות, matanot, do you give half or
not when it's a half בהמה behemah because רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
says half is nothing. How about the כיסוי הדם Kisuy Hadam case?
The כיסוי הדם Kisuy Hadam case, this is half this is half
בהמה, behemah, possibly half חיה, chayah, so רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says
if it's only if the most it can be is half חיה,
chayah, that's nothing. You don't cover the blood. Half is nothing. You
don't cover the blood, it's not it's certainly not full חיה. chayah.
But the rabbis say, since it's possible it's half חיה, chayah, that
is enough to cover the blood מספק, misafek, because half would be
enough to say do it. Okay? So that's the case that they
debate. It is definitely half בהמה, behemah, it is possibly half חיה.
chayah. The rabbis say half is enough, half is enough to give
מתנות. matanot. The ספק safek half חיה chayah is enough to cover
the blood. And רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says half is nothing, don't
give the מתנות, matanot, don't cover the blood. That's that. לעניין אותו
ואת בנו, Le'inyan Oto Ve'et Beno, how about the debate of אותו
ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, whether you're חייב chayav when you שחט
shecht a כוי koy if the כוי koy is the mother?
משכחת ליה, Mishtakchas lei, you can find it בין תייש הבא על
הצביה בין צבי הבא על התיישה, bein tayish haba al hatzviyah bein
tzvi haba al hatayishah, whether it is the mother is a חיה
chayah or the mother is a בהמה. behemah. Let's spell it out.
בתייש הבא על הצביה, Be'tayish haba al hatzviyah, if it is the
male goat with the with the female צביה, tzviyah, so therefore the
mother is a is a חיה chayah ולאיסורא, ule'issura, then the debate
is not whether you get lashes, the debate is whether it is
prohibited. So here's the case, its mother is a חיה, chayah, its
father is a בהמה. behemah. So this animal is definitely half חיה,
chayah, questionably half בהמה. behemah. So in that case, right, everybody get
that? Right, definitely half חיה, chayah, possibly half בהמה. behemah. So according
to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, would this be prohibited? Worst case scenario,
this animal is half בהמה. behemah. So is it prohibited if it's
half בהמה, behemah, רבי אליעזר? Rebbi Eliezer? No. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
says half is nothing, right? So therefore, according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer it's totally permissible. Worst case scenario it's half בהמה, behemah, half
is nothing, totally permissible. According to the rabbis, if it's half בהמה,
behemah, is it prohibited? Yes, right, because half counts. But it's only
questionably half בהמה, behemah, so you'll never give a guy lashes for
this because you don't know for certain that it's half בהמה, behemah,
you don't know for certain you consider the father. So therefore he
says ולאיסורא, ule'issura, it's not about lashes, it's about whether we should
prohibit. Yes.
Why are we using the question questionably half בהמה? behemah?
Because the father is a בהמה, behemah, the mother is a חיה.
chayah.
He's definitely a בהמה, behemah, right?
No, the father is definitely a בהמה, behemah, but the question is
does the child oh,
the child yeah. The father's a בהמה, behemah, the father's a בהמה
behemah and the mother's a חיה. chayah. Right. So what is the
status of the child, right? People say, right, I'm one quarter Indian,
I'm one half African American or whatever, right? So this here, this
animal, this כוי, koy, is definitely half חיה chayah because its mother's
a חיה. chayah. Is it 100 percent חיה chayah or is it
half חיה, chayah, half בהמה? behemah? We don't know, it depends whether
you care about the father's contribution or not. So therefore the second
half of it is questionable whether you consider that to be half
חיה chayah or half בהמה. behemah.
Just how you consider the father.
Exactly. Okay? So in this case, you in this case רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer says worst case scenario half בהמה, behemah, not an issue,
I don't care about half, go ahead and שחט shecht it. חכמים
Chakhamim say if it's half בהמה, behemah, it's אסור assur and you
get מלקות. malkos. But we don't know if it's half בהמה, behemah,
so therefore it's prohibited but you don't get מלקות. malkos. So therefore
it says ולאיסורא. ule'issura. The worst case is that we'd say don't
do it, nobody's going to give you lashes. רבנן סברי, Rabanan savri,
the rabbis say דילמא חיישינן לזרע האב, dilma chayshinan lezera ha'av,
maybe the father's contribution matters and therefore it's half בהמה, behemah, and
if it's half בהמה, behemah, סבר אפילו מקצת אמרינן, savar afilu mikzat
amrinan, it would be we would we would care that it's half
בהמה behemah ואסור, ve'assur, and it would be forbidden. Now if we
knew that you'd get lashes, but we don't know for certain it's
half בהמה, behemah, so therefore don't do it. רבי אליעזר סבר, Rebbi
Eliezer savar, and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says מיהא נמי דחיישינן לזרע
האב, miha nami dechayshinan lezera ha'av,
even if you consider the father's contribution, even if I were to
grant you that this would be half בהמה, behemah, סבר אפילו מקצת
לא אמרינן, savar afilu mikzat lo amrinan, I don't care if something
is only halfway, if it's only half בהמה behemah it's nothing and
it's not prohibited. So that's the case about is it prohibited by
אותו ואת בנו Oto Ve'et Beno if it's a כוי? koy? So
in this case where it's definitely half חיה chayah possibly half בהמה,
behemah, so it is the debate of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and
the rabbis, but everybody agrees you don't get lashes because worst case
scenario it's half בהמה behemah but we don't even know if that's
true. Now, that's one scenario.
אבל חנניה Aval Chananya though.
חנניה Chananya okay. Michael, let's get through these scenarios and then you
can say. Okay. So now, here's another scenario where they could be
debating אותו ואת בנו, Oto Ve'et Beno, בצבי הבא על התיישה, betzvi
haba al hatayishah, where the father is a חיה chayah and the
mother is a בהמה, behemah, the mother is the goat. So in
that case it is definitely half בהמה, behemah, maybe 100 percent בהמה.
behemah. Got it? Because the mother is the goat and the father
is the צבי, tzvi, so it's definitely half בהמה, behemah, whether you
consider the father or not it might be 100 percent בהמה. behemah.
So according to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, if it was half בהמה,
behemah, could you שחט shecht it? This is not a rhetorical question.
Can you שחט shecht it? Yes, well whatever, it's not אותו ואת
בנו Oto Ve'et Beno if it's only half בהמה. behemah. But if
it was 100 percent בהמה, behemah, then you could be חייב. chayav.
might be 100% בהמה. behema. So he would say don't שחט shecht
it because it might be 100% בהמה behema and prohibited, but you
won't get lashes because you don't know for sure. According to the
Rabbis if it's half בהמה, behema, can you שחט shecht it? No.
Do you get lashes? Yes, because half is enough. So therefore in
this case everybody agrees don't do it, but the debate would be
whether you get lashes or not, okay?
So ולמלקות, u'l'malkos, the debate is about lashes. רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri,
the Rabbis hold, והאי נמי דחיישינן לזרע האב, v'hai nami d'chaishinan l'zera
ha'av, even if the father's contribution matters, here the father is a
חיה, chaya, so this animal is only half בהמה, behema, even if
it's only half בהמה, behema, סברא אפילו מקצת אמרינן, sevara afilu miktzas
amrinan, half is enough, and therefore you would get lashes, ומלקינן ליה,
u'malkinan lei, you give him lashes, even if only half בהמה, behema,
once it's half it's enough. ורבי אליעזר סבר, v'Rabbi Eliezer savar, Rabbi
Eliezer holds, איסורא איכא מלקות ליכא, issura ika malkus leka, don't do
it, there's a prohibition, but I can't give you lashes. איסורא איכא,
issura ika, why is there a prohibition? דילמא אין חוששין לזרע האב,
dilma ein chosheshin l'zera ha'av, maybe the father's contribution doesn't matter, והאי
בהמה מעליא הוא, v'hai behema l'alya hu, and this is a full
בהמה behema because it only goes by the mother. And then if
I knew that for sure, I'd give you lashes.
והאי... ובהמה מעליא הוא. v'hai... v'behema l'alya hu. מלקות ליכא, malkus leka,
but I can't give you lashes. Why not? דילמא חוששין לזרע האב,
dilma chosheshin l'zera ha'av, maybe the father's contribution matters, והוי פלגא בהמה,
v'havai palga behema, and it therefore this is only a half בהמה
behema because the father makes it a half
חיה, chaya, וסברא אפילו מקצת לא אמרינן, v'sevara afilu miktzas lo amrinan,
and if it's only a half בהמה behema I can't give you
lashes. So that was nice, thank you very much, Papa Bear, that's
very clear. He had a whole קאפ, kop, but it was very
clear, he spelled it all out, and basically what we're saying is
like now as we have the following factors to consider in all
of these cases. Number one is
possibly you always consider the father, you're always חיישינן לזרע האב, chaishinan
l'zera ha'av, or possibly you completely reject the father, or what the
גמרא Gemara seems to be gravitating towards in all of its different
opinions is the middle position. We don't know, we have to play
it safe and be in doubt, and do you consider the father
or not. The other factor is, and that's what the רבנן Rabbanan
introduced here is, what does the הלכה halacha demand in any particular
circumstance? When the הלכה halacha makes a distinction between חיה chaya and
בהמה, behema, if you have something that's half and half, is it
in or is it out? And that's saying that this is the
real debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן. Rabbanan. The
רבנן Rabbanan say when it demands something half is enough, and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if you're not full then you're out of
the category, with practical implications for not only for prohibition, for prohibitions,
for covering the blood, for giving the gifts, whenever the תורה Torah
demands something, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you have to be
completely in the category, and according to the רבנן Rabbanan it's enough
that you are half in the category. You mentioned...
you can't שחט shecht in the house outside the sanctuary.
You can't שחט, shecht, if it's a קרבן korban you can't שחט
shecht it outside.
So why would they say no, not שחט? shecht? שחטת אותו ואת
בנוing shecht אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es beno.
Oh, אותו ואת בנו, oso v'es beno, yeah.
I just
wanted to make sure I'm getting all this in conjunction and in
context with like all the other opinions we had before, which is
like חנניה, Chananya, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and all that. Yes. So
these חכמים chachamim are only according to the who? Who's חנניה? Chananya?
We don't know what חנניה Chananya and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
hold in terms of this question about does half count? That was
not their discussion. Okay, we don't know about what they would hold
about that, right? We know their question was not a question of
something that's half and half, but do you are you חייב chayav
for father and child? Right? So for them, they weren't dealing with
a half case. All we know for them is that according to
חנניה Chananya father matters and according to... you do count the father
and definitely therefore you would give lashes, it's not a ספק, safek,
for him ודאי vaday the father matters. And for the רבנן, Rabbanan,
it sounds like the father definitely does not matter, although possible the
Rabbis have a ספק. safek. But we have no idea what they
would hold about the question about half in half out because they
weren't dealing with that case.
Yeah, but if you say the father matters, you could say half
in?
No, the thing is a 100% חיה, chaya, it has a father
that's a חיה chaya and a mother that's a חיה. chaya. It's
not a half identity, right? The question was is that is the
father part of the family? Okay, so all we know is that
חנניה Chananya said you are definitely חיישינן לזרע האב, chaishinan l'zera ha'av,
he didn't have a ספק, safek, he said you're ודאי חיישינן. vaday
chaishinan. Here they're holding ספק, safek, but we have no idea what
he would say about a half case. Okay.
You're going to try to figure that out?
No. Now the גמרא Gemara continues, now that we are done with
that which was, which was like I said, you know, straightforward but
you had a whole קאפ. kop. Now we are sort of moving
from the question about חיישינן לזרע האב chaishinan l'zera ha'av which, as
I said, is a question that comes up a number of places
in ש"ס, Shas, and I'll just repeat what I said yesterday which
is it's not always the same question. Since Michael just mentioned the,
you know, the חנניה Chananya issue, there I think it's an easier
question. There the question is do you consider the father part of
the family unit? Is there a sense of a relationship between father
and child in the animal world, right? This is a question in
the animal world where you don't have the family structure that you
have in human society. That's I think a very, you know, reasonable
question. I think what's harder to understand is the גמרא Gemara here
which is in terms of saying is this animal half בהמה behema
half חיה, chaya, you know, it's about the very identity, you'd think
that's about genetic makeup, and of course you consider the father's contribution.
We could question whether half counts, that’s the issue here, whether שם
אפילו מקצתה, shem afilu miktzatah,
but it’s strange to think that it’s its very sort of identity
is not determined also by the contribution of the father. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara does combine the two discussions, but there are other
cases where the issue of חשינן לזרע האב chashinan le-zera ha-av comes
up and they’re not always seen, the questions are not always treated
in the same manner. Okay, now we shift from חשינן לזרע האב
chashinan le-zera ha-av to discuss כוי koy since we brought it up,
and we're going to spell out some other opinions about כוי. koy.
So let's take a look.
Give me the next case? I like that.
No. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehudah. So Rav Yehuda said, כוי
בריה בפני עצמה היא, koy biryah bifnei atzmah hi, ולא הכריעו בה
חכמים אם מין בהמה היא אם מין חיה. ve-lo hikhri'u bah chakhamim
im min behemah hi im min chayah. So he actually accepts, and
it's very clear, it's not clear from this statement but it's clear
in other contexts, rejects the idea that it's a crossbreed. It's quite
fascinating. Like, did they ever see a כוי? koy? Was there a
tradition that there was this animal called כוי koy that they knew
was debated and then they were trying to figure out what it
was? Because you would think if they actually saw a כוי, koy,
they could do a little investigation and find out how it was
born and where it came from.
Wait, until now we've been assuming the כוי, koy, how is it
produced?
That we don't know. Until now we've been assuming it can produce,
but the
father is one thing...
Until now we've been assuming it's a crossbreed of a, of a
goat and whatever, a צבי. tzvi. But Rav Yehuda says that it's
not a hybrid, it's not a crossbreed, it's its own species.
But does it matter when we say כוי, koy, which parent is
it?
Of course it matters. That's what we've been discussing until now.
No, but is it still a כוי koy whether the father is...
Yes, it's still a כוי, koy, but the הלכות halakhot might be
different. Since we know the mother's contribution matters and the father's contribution
is questionable, the הלכות halakhot might be different, but we'll still call
it a כוי. koy. Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Okay, so now we move from a discussion between תנאים Tanna'im to
a discussion between אמוראים, Amora'im, which is a change of place. They
don't have a כוי. koy.
Right, right, you're absolutely correct. Right, you know, and that, thank you,
you know, I didn't note that, but that actually makes sense because
here the reflections on what a כוי koy is, is really discussed
at the time of the אמוראים Amora'im where all they knew was
the Tannaitic, you know, debates about כוי, koy, but they probably didn't
know what was being talked about, so they were trying, speculating. Right.
So until now we've been sort of assuming that a כוי koy
is a, is a hybrid, but now we're going to speculate maybe
it's its own species. Okay. So אמר רב יהודה כוי בריה בפני
עצמה היא. Amar Rav Yehuda koy biryah bifnei atzmah hi.
It's not a hybrid, it's its own species. ולא הכריעו בו חכמים
אם מין בהמה היא אם מין חיה. ve-lo hikhri'u bo chakhamim im
min behemah hi im min chayah. And the Rabbis, it wasn't because
it was half and half and therefore it fell between categories. You
know, the Rabbis didn't know whether to consider this a בהמה behemah
or a חיה. chayah. And you know, like people were saying, like
the questions came up in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim about
European buffalo, is that, is that a בהמה? behemah? חיה? chayah? Exactly
what's the determining line? If you remember the גמרא Gemara earlier, right,
said the basic way you determine was based on like what the
horns looked like. So look at תוספות, Tosafot, for example. תוספות Tosafot
says, ולא הכריעו חכמים אם מין בהמה אם מין חיה. ve-lo hikhri'u
chakhamim im min behemah im min chayah. So says תוספות, Tosafot, ואם
תאמר ולבדוק בסימני דקרניים, ve-im tomar ve-livdok be-simanei di-karnayim, check the horns,
because we had a whole גמרא Gemara before about the horns determining.
ויש לומר דאפשר דלא היו יכולים לברר בקרניו שפיר אם חדודות וכרוכות
טפי. ve-yesh lomar de-efshar de-lo hayu yekholim levarer be-karnav shapir im chadudot
ve-khrukhot tefei.
You know, things sometimes, you know, if you say they have to
be ridged and they have to be this, well, how ridged is
ridged? How, you know, how pointy is pointy? You know, there's questions
about whether something really satisfies the criteria or not. So he says
a very reasonable thing. This was a type of a kosher animal
that they could not figure out which category to put it in.
And all the debate that we have before of do you have
to do כיסוי הדם, kisuy ha-dam, why is there a ספק safek
whether you have to do כיסוי הדם? kisuy ha-dam? It's simply because
we don't know, is it a בהמה behemah or is it a
חיה, chayah, right? So, and so now that you'd have to go
figure out how they're debating whether you're חייב chayav for אותו ואת
בנו, oto ve-et beno, because, you know, you would think if it's
a ספק, safek, everybody should agree don't do it, but if you
do it you don't get lashes. But anyway, he says it is
not a hybrid, it is a ספק. safek. I don't know. He
doesn't, he doesn't spell out how he would translate in that case.
What is the difference between בהמה behemah and חיה? chayah? One is
domesticated...
Yes, but how do you define what, how much domesticated? How it
lives. Possibly, but it's again, it's not, it's not a particular circumstance
of domesticated, it's whether you consider the species domesticated. Also, what happens
if you have, we're going to see in a few lines from
now, what happens if a segment of the species is domesticated? What
does it, how do you define the rest of it? If you
have wild goats and you have goats that are domesticated, are wild
goats בהמה behemah or wild goats חיה? chayah? Is it that all
of goats are now considered בהמה behemah or only the domesticated line
is? So those are things that are not well determined, and that's
why there can be doubt.
So according to this, that goat went extinct? We just don't know
what it is?
Yeah, presumably, I don't know. So let's keep on going. What is
not clear is why there would be a debate about things like
אותו ואת בנו, oto ve-et beno, right, but okay, but that's his,
Rav Yehuda's approach. רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, Rav Nachman says,
again, as Avigail pointed out, we're in the אמוראים, Amora'im, so they
are more speculating what the כוי koy is, כוי זה איל הבר.
koy zeh ayal ha-bar. Now, this כוי koy is the wild or
the, or the, the ram of the, of the forest. Okay, which
sounds like it's a חיה, chayah, but it's not clear. We... know
it's debated, so presumably what he means is, is his point that
on the one hand it's a ram, but on the other hand
it lives in the forest. So is it a חיה, chayah, is
it a בהמה? behemah? That's where the doubt comes from. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, let's see how it continues.
I don't know by the way, anyway, by the way, I shouldn't
say, I'm not sure that that's because איל ayal is... it's not
איל ayil is a ram, but איל ayal is... what's an איל?
ayal? A deer, a hart, a deer or something? So, of course
if it was a deer, then you wouldn't understand why it was
debated whether it was a חיה chayah or בהמה. behemah. So it
seems like he's saying that it's a ram of the forest. Okay,
so let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues.
Where are we?
Right, רש״י's Rashi actually clear. רש״י Rashi says איל זכר הגדול ביערים.
ayal zachar hagadol beye'arim. זכר Zachar meaning a ram, a male ram.
Okay. יש אומרים זה הבא מן התיש ומן הצבי. Yesh omrim ze
haba min hatayish umin hatzvi. And that's what we've been assuming until
now, it's a crossbreed between a goat and a צבי. tzvi. Okay,
which explains why we've been debating things like אותו ואת בנו. oto
ve'et beno. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר, omer, now which... now that...
that was אמוראים. Amoraim. Now we are shifting to... what do you
call it? To תנאים, Tannaim, because now we are quoting רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi and if you look at the side this is from
a תוספתא. Tosefta. Okay, so it's funny, because here we will see
that it is... there was also opinions even within the תנאים. Tannaim.
Right. כוי בריה בפני עצמה היא ולא הכריעו בה חכמים אם מין
בהמה אם מין חיה. Koi biryah bifnei atzmah hi velo hichri'u bah
chachamim im min behemah im min chayah. So now it's funny that
we started with the אמוראים Amoraim and now we're going to find
the exact same issue is debated in the תנאים. Tannaim. Yes, so
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says exactly this, it's its own species, we
don't know what it is. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מין בהמה
היא. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer min behemah hi. Actually it's a
בהמה. behemah. Now according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel he would say none of these debates make sense. I don't...
I don't, you know, I don't acknowledge any of these debates, or
I think all these debates were because of a misunderstanding, but personally
I think it's clear that it's a בהמה behemah and therefore its
status is clear. ושל בית דושי veshel beit Dushai or דושאי Dushai
היו מגדלין מהן עדרים עדרים. hayu megadlin mehen adarim adarim. And I
know this family that would raise flocks and flocks of this, which
first of all proves that it's not a hybrid, it's its own
species, and he... and he claims that it was a בהמה. behemah.
So according to him, all those debates were not valid.
Which is funny, the whole thing about, you know, בין השמשות, bein
hashemashot, אליה ונימא, aleyha venima, then רבין... Ravin... רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
אני אומר... ani omer... ראיתי... ra'iti...
Right, so maybe they... disagreed with him that that was what a
כוי... Koi... you saw interesting things, but we don't say it's a
כוי. Koi. So it's... it's quite fascinating that there were debates about
a כוי Koi and then as Avigail points out, not only אמוראים
Amoraim didn't know what it was and speculated, but even some of
the תנאים, Tannaim, right, sort of were uncertain what was this animal
and the nature of this animal that was being debated. אמר רבי
זירא אמר רב ספרא אמר רב המנונא. Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Safra amar Rav Hamnuna. Now that we're talking about questionable חיה, chayah,
questionable בהמה, behemah, we stick on this for a little bit while
longer. So let's take a look. הני עיזי דבאלא, Hanei izei devala,
which is... which is basically what the גמרא Gemara said... which is
rams of the... or not rams, goats of the forest. באלא Bala
is... means forest. כשירות לגבי מזבח. Keshirut legabei mizbe'ach. So here this...
this takes us on your... on your point Charlie, because they are
goats, all species of goats are the same and therefore they are
a בהמה, behemah, and therefore they can be used for the altar.
Once goats are acknowledged as something you bring on the altar, all
goats are the same. Okay? So you'd say the same... איל הבר
ayal habar then, right? Right, and presumably an איל הבר ayal habar
would be the same, would be a ram, would be כשר kasher
for the altar and would be a בהמה. behemah. סבר לה כי
הא דאמר רבי יצחק, Savar lah ki ha de'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, so
he holds like what רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak said. עשר בהמות מנה
הכתוב וכולו. Esser behemot manah hakatuv vekhulo. The Torah only lists ten
types of kosher animals when the Torah lists kosher animals and there
are no other kosher animals. So any other kosher animal you find,
you have to put into one of the ten. What are the
ten? So רש״י Rashi tells you, it's the first wide line. שור
שה כשבים ושה עזים איל וצבי ויחמור ואקו ודישן ותאו וזמר. Shor
seh kshavim veseh izim ayal utzvi veyachmur ve'akko vedishon vete'o vazamer. Oops,
I only counted nine. שור, Shor, excuse me, שור שה כשבים ושה
עזים, Shor seh kshavim veseh izim, so that's your ox, your sheep,
and your goat, right? איל וצבי ויחמור, Ayal utzvi veyachmur, which are
different types of deer, ואקו ודישן ותאו וזמר, ve'akko vedishon vete'o vazamer,
which we don't know what those are. So those are ten animals,
three בהמות, behemot, presumably seven חיות, chayot, and the... and that's in
the Torah. So the claim is any kosher animal has to be
one of these ten. So any kosher animal has to be one
of these ten and you're finding a wild goat, so presumably which
category would you put it in? The goat. So therefore by definition
if it's a goat, it's a בהמה behemah even if this... even
if this brand is wild, and therefore you can use it on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Yeah, unless there's... might be that wild goats will
breed with domestic goats.
Ah, okay, there you go.
Even if they're supposedly a different species that they wouldn't interbreed.
Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so therefore ומדלא
קחשיב להו בהדי הני חיות, umidela kachashiv lehu behadei hanei chayot, and
these wild goats, מדלא קחשיב להו בהדי חיות, midela kachashiv lehu behadei
chayot, since they're not amongst the seven חיה chayah species, so שמע
מינה דעיזים נינהו, shma mina de'izim ninhu, so they're in the goat
category and they're a בהמה. behemah. מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב,
Matkif lah Rav Acha bar Yaakov, so now you see the difficulty
of distinguishing between בהמה behemah and חיה chayah is number one, even
if you have an independent species, sometimes its characteristics aren't clear, like
the כוי, Koi, and sometimes if you have two strands of a
species, right, how do they get defined if one part is definitely
a בהמה. behemah. The eighth minute, so it goes to the end
and the whole category in there of בהמה. Behemah. So מתקיף לה
רב אחא בר יעקב, Maskif lei Rav Acha bar Yaakov, ואימא, ve'eima,
why don't we say יהבי yahvei פרט, perat, כל בהמה kol behemah
כלל, klal, פרט וכלל נעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט, perat veklal na'aseh
klal mosif al haperat, איכא טובא? ika tuva? Who tells you that
these ten are the only kosher animals? Maybe the Torah gave examples
and then it said any animal that has split hoofs, right, that's
how we logically read the פסוקים. pesukim. It says any בהמה behemah
with split hoofs, it lists some kosher ones, and then it says
as long as it has split hoofs. So these are examples but
it's not the full list. Why didn't you say that? So the
answer is no, אם כן כל הני פרטי למה לי, im ken
kol hanei peratei lamah li, then why does the Torah have to
give examples? Just tell me the characteristics. So since it gave examples,
which is funny, you know you think that's always the question about
a כלל klal and a פרט perat and a פרט perat and
a כלל, klal, right, you could always say why did you give
examples if you didn't mean to limit it? But anyway, here's an
approach that says it is not just the characteristics don't suffice. We
have to assume that any kosher animal falls into these ten categories.
I know, so it's ignoring all that.
So מתקיף לה רב אחא בריה דרב איקא. Maskif lei Rav Acha
brei deRav Ika. So Rav Acha brei deRav Ika asks, ודלמא מיני
דעז נינהו? vedilma minei de'aza ninhu? OK, so you said it has
to be into one of these categories. But who tells you put
wild goat into the goat category? Right, there are other things here
which we don't even know what they are. אקו תאו וזמר, ako
te'o vezamer, maybe it's one of those? Right. So maybe it's a
חיה chayah one of those that we don't know? So אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי amar lei Rav Acha brei deRava
leRav Ashi ואמרי לה רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לרב אשי. ve'amri
lah Rav Acha brei deRav Avya leRav Ashi. So one of them
says to Rav Ashi, דלמא מיני דתאו או מיני דזמר נינהו? dilma
minei deteo o minei dezamer ninhu? So the other ones we just
mentioned, it says אקו תאו וזמר. ako te'o vezamer. We have no
idea what those are. So fine, maybe we're on this wild goat,
who allows you to put it into the standard goat category? So
אמר ליה רב חנן לרב אשי. amar lei Rav Chanan leRav Ashi.
So Rav Chanan says to Rav Ashi: OK, I hear, so these
people are telling it to Rav Ashi, we should be concerned it's
a חיה chayah and put it into those other categories. So Rav
Chanan reported to Rav Ashi, you should know Rav Ashi, אמימר שרי
תרבייהו, Amemar shari tarbeihu, that Amemar said the fat was permitted. Which
means that according to Amemar, this wild goat was a... no, if
the fat is permitted it's a חיה, chayah, right? בחיה bechayah the
fat is permitted. So he said it was definitely a חיה. chayah.
So we have one person who's saying it's definitely a בהמה behemah
and you can bring it as a קרבן, korban, and we have
somebody else saying it's wild, if it's wild it's definitely a חיה
chayah and even the fat is permitted. So here you can see
how there could be doubts about how you categorize. בעי מיניה אבא
בריה דרב מניומי בר חייא מרב הונא בר חייא. Ba'ei minei Abba
brei deRav Minyumi bar Chiyya meRav Huna bar Chiyya. So this question
was asked from the grandson of Rav Chiyya to Rav Huna the
son of Rav Chiyya. הני עיזי דבאלי hanei izzi deba'ali basically the
exact same question, goats of the forest, he asked his father, right,
or uncle, right, uncle because his father was Minyumi. So he asked
his uncle, right, so these goats of the forest, מהו לגבי מזבח?
mahu legabei mizbe'ach? Exactly the same question. But now it's being posed
to Rav Huna. Or no, yeah, Rav Huna. So אמר ליה עד
כאן לא פליגי ר' יוסי ורבנן אלא בשור הבר. amar lei ad
kan lo peligi Rabbi Yose veRabbanan ela be'shor habar. Until now we
know that there's a debate about the wild ox. דתנן detnan we
have a משנה, mishnah, שור הבר מין בהמה הוא, shor habar min
behemah hu, the wild ox is a type of a בהמה. behemah.
ר' יוסי אומר מין חיה Rabbi Yose omer min chayah that it's
a type of a חיה. chayah. So it seems to be the
same debate, right? It's a species that is domesticated but this is
one part of that that is still wild. Do you consider it
a בהמה behemah or חיה? chayah? So you would think that isn't
this exactly the same debate, let's apply it here? But he says
no, they're only debating that case. Why? And that it's not the
same as this. Why is it not the same? דרבנן סברי מדמתרגמינן
תורבלא מינא דבהמה הוא. deRabbanan savri mide'metargeminan turbala mina debehemah hu. The
תרגום Targum this is quite fascinating, using the תרגום Targum for a
הלכה halachic purpose. OK, so the תרגום Targum of which word? The
word of תאו, te'o, right? Remember it lists תאו ויחמור ואקו ודישון
וזמר te'o veyachmur ve'ako vedishon vezamer amongst the חיות. chayot. So תאו,
te'o, the תרגום Targum is תורבלא. turbala. Now תורבלא, turbala, split it
up, תור ברא, tor bara, an ox of the forest. OK, so
therefore the תרגום Targum of תאו te'o is exactly this case, שור
הבר, shor habar, an ox of the forest. One minute. מינא דבהמה
הוא. mina debehemah hu. Since that now, you would think, OK, but
since that's the תרגום Targum of תאו, te'o, and תאו te'o is
in the part of the פסוק pasuk that deals with חיות, chayot,
you would think that let's call it a חיה. chayah. Ironically, he
says no, since how somehow he's using the word שור shor in
the תרגום, Targum, it's a בהמה, behemah, which is quite bizarre. The
next line is the more logical position. ור' יוסי סבר, veRabbi Yose
savar, Rabbi Yose says no, the opposite. מדקחשיב ליה בהדי חיות, midekachshiv
lei bahadi chayot, even if תאו te'o that's dealing with חיות. chayot.
So מינא דחיה היא, mina dechayah hi, it's a type of a
חיה, chayah, which is of course the logical thing. You wonder what
the first point was, but the first point seems to be that
since the word used is שור shor to describe it, that labels
it as בהמה, behemah, which is strange though. Again, the real point,
the stronger point seems to be if תאו te'o is this wild
ox, it's in the part of the פסוק pasuk that deals with
חיות. chayot. They were talking about תרגום אונקלוס, Targum Onkelos, whether the
גמרא's Gemara תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos is our... Targum Onkelos תרגום אונקלוס
Targum Onkelos is Targum Onkelos תרגום אונקלוס. Targum Onkelos. Onkelos אונקלוס Onkelos
was a student of Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. It was
Tannaitic. I think it's like early second century if I remember correctly,
okay, was the Targum תרגום, Targum, and there are things that are
being written, you know, there's definitely scholarship about how much is the
Targum
Onkelos תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos referred to in
the Gemara גמרא Gemara exactly the same as our Targum Onkelos תרגום
אונקלוס Targum Onkelos and so forth. I did not check the pasuk
פסוק. pasuk What, yeah, there's definitely some Targum תרגום. Targum. I did
not check the pasuk פסוק. pasuk. What do you have? Here's the
animal's English name is tur and it's a wild goat. That's interesting.
And here we're talking about wild goat, izzibali עזיבאלי. izzibali. Okay, anyway,
yes. What if it's the Targum תרגום, Targum, you know, also didn't
know and that's just his interpretation and so why do they change
it because the Targum תרגום Targum says? I mean, we have Tannaim
תנאים Tannaim that have a whole debate. All because the Targum תרגום
Targum says so? I understand, that's why I said that it is
unusual that we use the Targum תרגום Targum in halachic purposes. But
presumably we're saying is that nobody is going to debate, the Targum
תרגום Targum was considered to be very authoritative, so unless you explicitly
you disagree, we're going to assume that everybody says that the te'o
תאו te'o is this wild ox. Okay. Exactly. Okay, so he's saying
the debate of the wild ox is because it was assumed to
be that that's what the te'o תאו te'o was referring to. So
the question was since te'o תאו te'o. is listed amongst the chayos
חיות, chayos, does that make it clear that this is a chaya
חיה chaya or not? Aval hani אבל הני, aval hani, but in
these cases, the wild goats, divei hakol mina de'izminhu דיבי הכל מינא
דעיזמינהו. divei hakol mina de'izminhu. Everybody would agree that it's a goat.
Meaning what he is saying is like this. If you have a
domesticated species and one part of it is still undomesticated and wild,
we would normally assume that the whole species is behema בהמה, behema,
even the wild part of it. The only reason there's a debate
about wild ox is because there is because that was in the
Torah's תורה Torah list, that was assumed to be what the Torah
תורה Torah referred to as te'o תאו. te'o. It was assumed to
be that the Torah תורה Torah had identified it as its own
species and included it in the chayas חיות chayas because that was
the Targum תרגום Targum of the word te'o תאו. te'o. So there
it's possible it's defined its own species and it's a chaya חיה.
chaya. But normally if you have a domesticated species, even the wild
branches of that family will still be considered to be behema בהמה,
behema, not chaya חיה. chaya. That was his approach. So his approach
was it was a behema בהמה, behema, but we're not done, let's
finish up. So matkiv lehu Rav Aha berei de'Ika מתקיף ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב איקא, matkif leh Rav Aha berei de'Ika, ve-dilma mina
de'ako ninhu ודילמא מינא דאקו נינהו? ve-dilma mina de'ako ninhu? He says
it's all very nice but you've accounted for the word te'o תאו.
te'o Who told you that the wild goat is not one of
these other chayos חיות chayos that are listed and maybe it's the
ako אקו? ako? Okay. Amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi, ve-dilma mina de'te'o ודילמא מינא
דתאו, ve-dilma mina de'te'o, which is funny because we already said that
te'o תאו was the wild ox but we're just really repeating what
we said above, o mina de-zamer ninhu או מינא דזמר נינהו? o
mina de-zamer ninhu? So it says it's all very nice that you're
saying that normally it's included in the behema בהמה behema category unless
it's its own category, but it might be its own category. We
don't know what these chayos חיות chayos are that are mentioned in
the Torah תורה. Torah. Amar leh Rav Papa le-Rav Ashi אמר ליה
רב פפא לרב אשי, amar leh Rav Papa le-Rav Ashi, Ameimar sharei
tarbaihu אמימר שרי תרבייהו. Ameimar sharei tarbaihu. If you want to know,
you're so certain it's a behema בהמה, behema, Ameimar אמימר Ameimar was
certain it was a chaya חיה chaya and Ameimar אמימר Ameimar would
even eat the fat of it. Okay, so we have a fascinating
debate here about what do you do with a, on the one
hand you have koi כוי koi which we fundamentally don't know how
to categorize. On the other hand you have something which you have
a domesticated strand and an undomesticated strand and do we give them
all the same label and call them behema בהמה behema or do
we say the undomesticated strand is a chaya חיה? chaya? And certainly
one factor is whether we could identify it as its own species
based on the Torah's תורה Torah listing of chayos חיות: chayos: te'o
ve-zamer ako dishon תאו וזמר אקו דישון te'o ve-zamer ako dishon etc.,
maybe it's one of those. But here we end by having Ameimar's
אמימר Ameimar position, which seems to be irrespective of whether it's in
the list in the Torah תורה, Torah, if this is a wild
species, if this is a wild branch then at least this branch
is considered to be chaya חיה. chaya. Okay, so here we have
a lot of questions around this distinction. Yes. What the PD says
the in captivity all species of goats can interbreed. Okay, so you
use the interbreeding as the definition that that would definitely be it.
Did you have a question though? What's Ameimar אמימר Ameimar say? Are
these categories necessarily not static because a wild strand can become domesticated?
Right. So is he saying that it's static or that it shifts?
Yeah that's a very good question, which is why when people say
domesticated non-domesticated, exactly, do we really mean that something can shift from
being a chaya חיה chaya to a behema בהמה? behema? The Gemara
גמרא Gemara earlier didn't sound that way. The Gemara גמרא Gemara earlier
sounded like the horns and whatnot, that things were not based on
whether we happen to domesticate them or not. So your question is
what's your question, why is it specifically around Ameimar אמימר? Ameimar? Why
would he be... but it's about the categorization. Yeah so it's you
know use hundreds of years to domesticate a species, maybe so but
over those years. I don't know the answer. All I can say
is that in all of the Gemara's גמרא Gemara discussion about chaya
חיה chaya and behema בהמה. behema. It never explicitly says. It is
true here it speaks about the wild one, the one in the
forest, but it never, but when it talks about what determines, if
you remember before, it was totally physical characteristics and here what's determining
is, do we allow one branch of the family to determine for
the other branch? But we're never, we've never said, you know, that
if you were to domesticate this, everybody would agree it would change.
It's possible that if you consider this to be a חיה chaya
and it has those types of horns, and you're of the position
that one half of the family doesn't determine for the other half,
it would remain a חיה chaya even if we somehow did domesticate
them. I don't know. But yeah, it is worth noting because in
general we speak about domesticated that that's not brought up here as
a real factor. Yes. How do we פסק pasken today for wild
goats, wild sheep? Oh, I don't know, that's a good question. I
assume like the buffalo, I assume we're מחמיר, machmir, we cover the
blood without a ברכה bracha and we don't eat the חלב. chelev.
Okay. We play it safe. Yes. חיה Chaya you're allowed to eat
the חלב. chelev. The way to remember this is that because the
חלב chelev doesn't go on the מזבח. mizbeach. When the חלב chelev
would go on the מזבח, mizbeach, it's forbidden. But the blood, but
the blood you cover for חיה, chaya, not for בהמה. behema. Forbidden,
it's all forbidden. Right. Correct. Okay. It is ironic, you know, the
whole thing about the blood and the חלב, chelev, I'll admit that,
because you would think that if this is a non-מזבח mizbeach species,
the blood would be seen as less potentially problematic. So the same
way the חלב chelev is less problematic and you can eat it,
you would think you wouldn't have to cover the blood. You would
think if anything you should cover the blood, if anything you would
think you should cover the blood by a בהמה, behema, right, because
that would be blood that otherwise would go on the מזבח. mizbeach.
So it's a little strange why the חלב chelev you do eat,
but the blood you have to cover. It's like on the one
hand we're being less sensitive about the חלב chelev of a חיה
chaya but almost more sensitive about the blood. So I don't really
have a good answer for that. Let's continue now. We move on
to the next part of the משנה. mishna. כיצד השוחט. Keitzad hashocheit.
Now the משנה mishna spoke, remember that all the permutations about חולין
chullin and קדשים kodshim that you're חייב chayav אותו ואת בנו oso
ve'es beno and other things you could be חייב chayav for, like
שחיטה shechita outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and all these
various things. But the פשט pshat was you're חייב chayav for חולין
chullin for whether you're חייב chayav אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es beno,
the second person who שחט, shachts, whether it doesn't have to be
the person who did the first שחיטה, shechita, only the second person
is חייב, chayav, and you're חייב chayav regardless of whether it's קדשים
kodshim or חולין, chullin, in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, out of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're always חייב chayav for אותו ואת
בנו oso ve'es beno at the second שחיטה. shechita. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אותו Oso first or בנו beno first?
It doesn't matter, right, whether you do the mother or the child
first. אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Oshaya, רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said,
כולא מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון. kulla masnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon. Our entire
משנה mishna is not like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Which רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? We'll tell you in a minute. ממה? Mima? How do
you know? מדקתני midekatni קדשים בחוץ, kodshim bachutz, הראשון חייב כרת והשני
פסול. harishon chayav kares vehasheni pasul. So the first guy gets כרת
kares for שחיטה shechting outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, both
animals are cannot be eaten because קרבן korban שחט shechted out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash can't be eaten, ושניהם סופגים את הארבעים,
ushneihem sofgin es ha'arba'im, both people get lashes, the first guy for
קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz and the second one for אותו ואת בנו.
oso ve'es beno. So מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. שמעינן ליה
לרבי שמעון, Shameinan lei l'Rabbi Shimon, we know that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon in general holds דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה. de'amar
shechita she'eina re'uya lo shema shechita. This is a concept that comes
up in many different contexts in ש"ס, Shas, which is when the
תורה Torah says if you שחט shecht something there are consequences. When
does the תורה Torah say if you שחט shecht something there are
consequences? Well, one is אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es beno. One is
something you might not have thought about, is when you steal a
sheep, a goat, a sheep or a cow and you slaughter it,
right, you pay four or five depending on whether it's a sheep
or a cow. Okay. So what happens if those slaughterings don't make
the meat כשר? kosher? If it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina
re'uya. Now there are a couple scenarios. One is let's say the
בהמה behema was a טריפה. treifa. Another is let's say the בהמה
behema was a שור הנסקל shor haniskal or was a בהמה behema
that was worshipped for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, or you were doing
a שחיטה shechita לעבודה זרה l'avoda zara and you made it אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Or what if the בהמה behema is a קרבן
korban that you're שוחט shechting out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
In all these cases the act of שחיטה shechita does not make
the meat permissible to be eaten. Is it considered a שחיטה shechita
for the consequences of paying four and five, אותו ואת בנו, oso
ve'es beno, all places where שחיטה shechita matters? Okay, so here is
the point. In our משנה mishna there were many scenarios where you
could not eat the meat of the second animal because it was
a קרבן korban outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or whatever
it was, and nevertheless we say you transgress אותו ואת בנו, oso
ve'es beno, which means that even when the שחיטה shechita does not
make the meat permissible, it's a שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she'eina re'uya,
it nevertheless counts as a שחיטה, shechita, שמה שחיטה, shema shechita, and
you transgress אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es beno. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying our entire משנה mishna is not like רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say if it's not ראויה,
re'uya, if it does not make the meat permissible, it doesn't count.
ואפילו הראשון, Ve'afillu harishon, right. Okay, so so let's take a look.
So קמא, kama, according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the first guy
who שחט shechted the קרבן korban outside of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, it would not have been considered a שחיטה. shechita. Before you
even say the second guy doesn't transgress, you only transgress if you
שחט shecht the mother and the child. You need the first שחיטה
shechita to count also, right? It's not just the second שחיטה, shechita,
both שחיטות shechitas have to count. So the first guy that שחט
shechted the קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מפתח
קטליה, mifta katlei, it's like he shot it in the head. It
doesn't count as a שחיטה. shechita. So שני, sheini, so by the
time you get to the second קרבן, korban, it's not, so here
the consequence, it's a little different than you would have thought, you
would have thought oh the second guy gets off because of שחיטה
שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya. That might be true, but actually in
this case he has, it's more negative the consequences. The first guy's
שחיטה shechita didn't count, so the second guy's קרבן korban out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is a קרבן korban that could have
been brought inside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So right, he's going
to now transgress more because now he'll have שחט shechted a קרבן
korban that could have been brought inside for שחיטה shechting it outside.
So שני, sheini, the second קרבן, korban, מיקרב בפנים הוא, mikrav bifnim
hu, is an animal that could have been accepted in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. There's no אותו ואת בנו oso v'es bno going
on here. So כרת נמי לחיוב. kares nami l'chayev. The second guy
should get כרת kares for שחיטה shechting an animal and the, well
the first one does. That's a good question. Rashi and Tosfos both
say this. If it was, if it's, if it's necessary in the
whole category, then we don't consider, you know, if by definition this
שחיטה shechita will always be אינה ראויה eina re'uya and the Torah
still says you transgress, we have to bracket it. So if the
Torah says you transgress by שחיטה shechting a קרבן korban out of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, why don't we say oh, I'm never
חייב chayav because every time I שחט shecht a קרבן korban out
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the שחיטה shechita is... So since
the Torah says you transgress, obviously for this prohibition it brackets the
fact that it was אינה ראויה. eina re'uya. But for other things
it's not bracketed. So therefore the first guy transgresses even though it
was אינה ראויה eina re'uya because that's the nature of שחוטי חוץ.
shchutei chutz. But since for other things it's not like a שחיטה,
shechita, the second animal, you're not going to get אותו ואת בנו
oso v'es bno with אינה ראויה, eina re'uya, but it could have
been brought in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's a קרבן korban
that's fit for the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and therefore you're חייב
chayav for... what's the case again? You שחט shechted both קרבנות korbanos
outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So חולין בפנים, chullin bifnim, if
it was חולין chullin in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so we
had said also that the, it can't be eaten because חולין בעזרה
chullin ba'azarah can't be eaten. But the second guy transgresses אותו ואת
בנו. oso v'es bno. So what does our משנה Mishna say? שניהם
פסולין, shneihem psulin, they both can't be eaten because it's חולין chullin
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, והשני סופג את הארבעים, v'hasheini sofeig
es ha'arbaim, the second guy gets lashes. מכדי, michdi, let's take a
look. שמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה.
shamin lei l'Rabbi Shimon d'amar shechita she'eina re'uya lo shma shechita. He
says it doesn't count. קמא, kama, so again, before you even get
to the second one, let's start with the first one because אותו
ואת בנו oso v'es bno requires two שחיטות. shechitas. So the first
guy מפתח קטליה, mifta katlei, it's like he shot it in the
head. It's not like he did a שחיטה shechita because when you
שחט shecht חולין chullin in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the meat
can't be eaten. So שני אמאי סופג את הארבעים, sheini amai sofeig
es ha'arbaim,
so why does the second guy get lashes?
Right? Because the second guy, it's not אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es
bno. The mother didn't have a שחיטה. shechita. Now you could have
also said the second guy doesn't get lashes because his שחיטה shechita
isn't a שחיטה shechita because it's in the, because it's meat that
can't be eaten. But either way, in this case of חולין בעזרה,
chullin ba'azarah, the second guy shouldn't get lashes. His שחיטה shechita doesn't
count because the meat can't be eaten and the first שחיטה shechita
didn't count because it was meat that couldn't be eaten. So the
second guy should never get lashes. Now yeah, in the משנה Mishna
the scenarios are two different people. קדשים בפנים, kodshim bifnim, now if
it's a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, what did
our משנה Mishna say? הראשון כשר, harishon kasher, the first is כשר
kasher obviously, it's a קרבן, korban, ופטור, ufatur, and you're exempt, and
not only exempt, you did a מצוה, mitzvah, you brought a קרבן
korban in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, והשני סופג את הארבעים, v'hasheini
sofeig es ha'arbaim, the second guy gets lashes because he's אותו ואת
בנו. oso v'es bno. It's not קדשים בחוץ, kodshim bachutz, but it's
אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es bno. So the גמרא Gemara says ופטור,
ufatur, but you can't eat it because it's a קרבן korban that
was not fit for a קרבן korban because the prohibition of אותו
ואת בנו oso v'es bno says you can't bring it that day
and therefore it doesn't count as a קרבן korban and you get
lashes for אותו ואת בנו oso v'es bno and you can't eat
it because it's a קרבן korban that was שחט shechted incorrectly. Okay,
so now the obvious point is, since it can't be eaten as
a קרבן, korban, right, why are you חייב chayav אותו ואת בנו?
oso v'es bno? But מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. שמעינן ליה
לרבי שמעון דאמר שחיטה שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה, shamin lei l'Rabbi
Shimon d'amar shechita she'eina re'uya lo shma shechita, that if it's not
fit it doesn't count. So שחיטת קדשים נמי שחיטה שאינה ראויה היא,
shechitas kodshim nami shechita she'eina re'uya hi, every שחיטה shechita of a
קרבן korban is not considered a שחיטה. shechita. Why not? דכמה דלא
זריק דם לא משתרי בשר. d'kama d'lo zarik dam lo mishtarei basar.
Normally by שחיטה, shechita, the very act of שחיטה shechita means that
the meat now can be eaten. By קדשים, kodshim, the meat is
forbidden to be eaten until you do the זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam,
until you put the blood on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So the שחיטה
shechita itself, although the meat is not going to remain forbidden, if
it's not sufficient to make the meat edible it's not called a
שחיטה. shechita. Now the גמרא Gemara is later going to say that
that's not so clear, that I mean give me a break, if
I were to kill the animal and not שחט shecht it I
couldn't be זורק zorek the דם. dam. The very fact that I
שחט shechted it which allows me to be זורק zorek the דם
dam proves that it has a status of שחיטה. shechita. But at
least the גמרא Gemara here is saying it's possible that I would
give... For other הלכות *halachos*, maybe for קרבנות korbanot *korbonos* yes, but
for other הלכות *halachos* I might not acknowledge that it's as a
שחיטה *shechita* because by itself it does not make the meat permitted.
Yes, so רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* is excluding קדשים *kodshim* from אותו
ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no, *oso ve'es beno*. Exactly. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to say that tomorrow. And that is exactly
true. That if now if you שחט shecht *shecht* קדשים *kodshim*, right,
even if you שחט shecht *shecht* it in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, yeah, you're never going to be חייב *chayav* for
אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no. *oso ve'es beno*. Now we can
talk about a case where the mother was חולין *chulin* and therefore
the mother what? Well I won't get into it right now. But
you have to think about, you know, here we're saying even the
first שחיטה *shechita* didn't count because because שחיטת קדשים *shechitas kodshim* doesn't
count and therefore obviously regardless of the second one, you're never חייב
*chayav* אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no. *oso ve'es beno*. So שני
למה סופג את הארבעים *sheini lamah sofeg es ha'arbayim*? Why do you
get lashes? ופסול *upasul*, why is it invalid actually? The second one
should be a good קרבן korban *korban* since the first one is
technically not a שחיטה *shechita*. The second one should not be a—for
אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no *oso ve'es beno*—and it should even
be a כשר קרבן korban *kasher korban*. Okay, so אלא *ella* what?
But it's also technically not a שחיטה *shechita* for אותו ואת בנו
oto ve-et b'no, *oso ve'es beno*, but it works for קרבנות korbanot
*korbonos*. So the second guy it should be a good, it's not
אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no, *oso ve'es beno*, the first שחיטה
*shechita* is not meaningful for that prohibition and therefore the second קרבן
korban, *korban* should be a good קרבן korban, *korban*. Yes. But when
we started this מסכת *masechta* we start out with who can שחט
shecht *shecht* and it didn't make a distinction between... Right. Because in
the world of קרבנות *korbonos*, clearly this is what counts as שחיטה
*shechita*. But what he's saying is when you look from the perspective
of other things, we have a generic definition of שחיטה *shechita* for
which this doesn't count. Within the world of קרבנות *korbonos*, this counts
as שחיטה *shechita*, but within the general concerns of שחיטה *shechita*, if
it doesn't make the meat permitted, it doesn't count, which is quite
bizarre because as opposed to all other שחיטות שאינן ראויות *shechitos she'einan
re'uyos* where the meat remains forbidden and it will never do anything,
this is obviously a stage in making the meat permitted. Okay. It
also gets the meat out of being a נבילה *neveila*, does all
those things. Even עולה *olah* is never שחיטה *shechita*? Well, because the
meat is never permitted. Well, I guess you would say, I mean,
right, given that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks about the אכילת מזבח
*achilas mizbeiach* and it's comparable to the אכילת אדם *achilas adam* or
אכילת כהנים *achilas kohanim*, I think you would say the same way
זריקת הדם *zerikas hadam* makes the blood of a חטאת *chatas* or
a שלמים *shlamim* ראוי לאכילה *raui la'achilah*, so it makes the meat
of an, you know, makes the meat for an עולה *olah* ראוי
לאכילת מזבח *raui la'achilas mizbeiach*, which we do say. So I don't
think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* would go that far, but it does
point out the strange aspect here that what we have always taken
as like the staples that you're doing an act of שחיטה *shechita*,
now we're actually saying from the perspective of other הלכות *halachos* what
you just did here doesn't count as a שחיטה *shechita*. It's quite
strange. Okay, אלא *ella* the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in a minute is
going to point out that that's not so obvious. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא שמע מינה דלא כרבי שמעון *ella shema mina
d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon*. We see that our entire משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* is
not like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* because so many cases in the
משנה Mishnah *mishnah* would be completely different according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* that says שחיטה שאינה ראויה *shechita she'eina re'uyah* doesn't count. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, פשיטא *pshita*, obviously, דהכי איתא *de'hachi issa*,
that's the case right here. Okay, why do you have to go
through such lengths to spell that out? רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says
שחיטה שאינה ראויה *shechita she'eina re'uyah* doesn't count and of course every
single line of the משנה *mishnah* is against it. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says exactly what was bothering us: שחיטת קדשים איצטריכא ליה
*shechitas kodshim itztricha lei*. No, no, no, it was important to spell
out what רבי שמעון'ס *Rabbi Shimon's* position would be by שחיטת קדשים
*shechitas kodshim*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka dachas amina* I would have thought
what everybody here says is thinking that שחיטת קדשים שחיטה ראויה היא
*shechitas kodshim shechita re'uyah hi*, that the שחיטה *shechita* of קדשים *kodshim*
counts as a שחיטה *shechita*, דהא אי נחר *de'ha ei nachar* if
you just killed it without a שחיטה *shechita* וזרק דם לא משתרי
בשר *ve'zarek dam lo mishtarei basar* the blood wouldn't be permitted so
it's not just killing it. Obviously it counts as שחיטה *shechita*, it's
what lets you do זריקת הדם *zerikas hadam*. וכי שחט shecht משתרי
בשר *ve'chi shachat mishtarei basar* when you do the שחיטה *shechita* correctly
it allows the meat to be eaten with the זריקת הדם *zerikas
hadam* ושחיטה ראויה היא *ve'shechita re'uyah hi* and therefore even רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* would say that the שחיטה *shechita* of כשר קדשים *kasher
kodshim* would count as שחיטה *shechita*. קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*
therefore we wanted to spell out that no, that רבי שמעון'ס *Rabbi
Shimon's* position—now nobody says how the גמרא *Gemara* knew this, but that
the גמרא *Gemara* is saying—that's why we wanted to spell it out,
that our assumption is רבי שמעון'ס *Rabbi Shimon's* position of שחיטה שאינה
ראויה *shechita she'eina re'uyah* would even apply to the world of כשר
קרבנות *kasher korbonos* and that a כשר קרבן korban *kasher korban* from
the perspective of other הלכות *halachos* what your שחיטה *shechita* of a
כשר קרבן korban. *kasher korban* is not considered a שחיטה *shechita*. So
the guy who came next, if you started by שחיטה *shechting* a
קרבן korban *korban*, the guy who came next would not be limited
by אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no, *oso ve'es beno* because what
you did from the perspective of other הלכות *halachos* is not a
שחיטה *shechita*. And as Charlie says, this is leading to say that
according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* there's no אותו ואת בנו oto
ve-et b'no, *oso ve'es beno* by קדשים *kodshim* because think about it,
if the mother was a קדשים *kodshim* then it's not a שחיטה
*shechita*, you're totally okay. If the mother was חולין *chulin* and then
the child or the second one was a קדשים *kodshim*, so okay,
there was a first שחיטה *shechita* but there will never be a
second שחיטה *shechita*, right? Because it's a קרבן korban *korban* outside of
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, it's אינה ראויה *eina re'uyah*.
Or let's say the second one is a קרבן korban *korban* in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, okay, it's also not a
שחיטה *shechita*, right? Because a שחיטה *shechita* of a קרבן korban, *korban*
is not a שחיטה *shechita*. So according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
you won't have it by קדשים *kodshim* and we're going to say
that explicitly tomorrow. Okay, so let's go a little bit further now.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: ולקי נמי משום לאו
lav, דמחוסר זמן *u'lki nami mishum lav d'mechusar zman*. So now we're
going to leave for a moment שחיטה שאינה ראויה *shechita she'eina re'uyah*
and ask a different question. When I שחט shechting *shecht* this animal,
this קרבן korban. *korban* that is prohibited to bring today as a
קרבן korban *korban* because its mother was שחט shechts *shechted* today, right?
It's not yet the time to bring it. It's like it's less
than eight days old. So therefore, that's why the משנה said that
it's a פסול pasul קרבן korban even if I שחט shechts it
in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, because I'm not allowed to שחט
shecht it today, and it's not its time. So the גמרא says,
well then why don't I get a lashes for bringing a קרבן
korban before its time? Like when the תורה Torah says, מיום השמיני
והלאה ירצה, mi-yom ha-shemini va-hal'ah yeiratzeh, we're going to learn that in
a minute, that actually I get lashes if I bring an animal
that's seven days old, less than eight days old as a קרבן,
korban and I שחט shechting it as a קרבן, korban I get
lashes because it says, we learn from the פסוק pasuk. לא ירצה,
lo yeiratzeh, which we learn to mean is, don't שחט as a
קרבן korban something that is not yet fit to be brought as
a קרבן. korban So why don't in this case, I also get
lashes not just for אותו ואת בנו, oto ve-et b'no, but in
the קרבן case also for שחט a קרבן when it's not its
time? ולוקמי נמי משום לאו דמחוסר זמן, veleukmei nami mishum lav demichusar
zman, because of the prohibition of something that is not yet its
time, דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, מנין לכל הפסולים
שבשור ובכשב שהוא בלא ירצה, minayin l'chol hapsulim shebashor uvasheh shehu belo
yeiratzeh, how do you know all things that are invalid by ox
and a sheep is in the prohibition of 'it shall not be
accepted', which is not seen as just descriptive, but is seen as
a prohibition: do not bring something that is not accepted, which means
if it has a מום, mum, if it's not yet the right
time, if it's in this case, אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et b'no,
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, ושור ושה שרוע וקלוט נדבה תעשה אתו ולנדר
לא ירצה. veshor vaseh sarua vekalut nedava ta'aseh oto uleneder lo yeiratzeh.
You can give it as a gift, which basically means as a
donation, but you can't bring it as a קרבן if it has
a מום. mum. And we're reading לא ירצה lo yeiratzeh as a
prohibition: you shall not try to bring it as a קרבן, you
shall not slaughter it as a קרבן. Okay, one minute. לימד על
הפסולים שבשור ושה שהוא בלא ירצה. limed al hapsulim shebashor vaseh shehu
belo yeiratzeh. We see that anything that's invalid and can't be brought,
you prohibit—it's prohibited. So why not the prohibition of bringing this קרבן
before its time? So the גמרא says no, כי קחשיב לאו דאותו
ואת בנו, ki kachashiv lav de'oto ve'et b'no, we're only counting prohibitions
when you get lashes for אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et b'no, לאוי
נוכראי, lavay nuchray, foreign לאוין, lavin, unrelated prohibitions, לא קחשיב, lo kachashiv,
we're not counting. So the גמרא says one minute, ולא? velo? Are
you not? והא קדשים בחוץ דלאוי נוכראי נינהו, veha kodashim bachutz delavay
nuchray ninhu, the קרבנות out of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash. that's
a foreign unrelated לאו, וקחשיב, vekachashiv, and that's mentioned in the משנה,
דקתני dekatani the משנה says, קדשים בחוץ הראשון חייב כרת והשני סופג
את הארבעים. kodashim bachutz harishon chayav kares vehasheni sofeg et ha-arba'im. You
get lashes for not just אותו ואת בנו oto ve-et b'no, but
for a קרבן out of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, the first
guy. So the גמרא says בשלמא שני משום לאו דאותו ואת בנו,
bishlama sheni mishum lav de'oto ve-et b'no, the second guy's lashes is
relevant, that's the lashes for אותו ואת בנו, oto ve-et b'no אלא
ראשון, ela rishon, the first guy's lashes when he slaughtered an animal
out of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, אמאי סופג? amai sofeg? Why
does he get lashes? לאו משום לאו דשחוטי חוץ? lav mishum lav
deshchutei chutz? It's because of the prohibition of a קרבן out of
the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash, So basically the גמרא is saying is
if we're mentioning all lashes and we are mentioning lashes of קרבנות
out of the בית המקדש, mention lashes for bringing a קרבן before
its time when you... if you can't bring it because of אותו
ואת בנו, you're bringing it before its time. So we'll just see
the answer and end with that for today. גמרא says no, כל
היכא דליכא לאו דאותו ואת בנו חשיב לאוי נוכראי. kol heicha deleika
lav de'oto ve-et b'no chashiv lavay nuchray. If you're going to talk
about the lashes for אותו ואת בנו, you're going to talk about
other lashes as well. וכל היכא, vechol heicha, I'm sorry, I said
that wrong. If the person doesn't get lashes for אותו ואת בנו,
the guy who first שחט the קרבן out of the בית המקדש,
so then we'll mention other lashes that he will get, like lashes
for שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. וכל היכא דאיכא לאו דאותו ואת בנו,
vechol heicha de'ika lav de'oto ve-et b'no, but if the guy does
get lashes for אותו ואת בנו, the second guy who transgressed אותו
ואת בנו, so therefore once we're already saying that the second guy
is getting lashes, לא חשיב לאוי נוכראי, lo chashiv lavay nuchray, we're
not going to bother mentioning other lashes that he'll get. So the
גמרא basically says the second guy who שחט a קרבן in the
בית המקדש, which he's not allowed to שחט for אותו ואת בנו,
not only does he transgress אותו ואת בנו, he transgresses שחט a
קרבן before its time because since אותו ואת בנו doesn't allow him
to bring it, since he transgresses that he gets lashes, we just
didn't bother to mention the lashes because we already told us that
he was getting one set of lashes, we don't bother mentioning he's
getting two sets of lashes. Okay, we will continue with this.